A Guide to the Virginia Social Science Association Records, 1927-1991
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Virginia Social Science Association Records, 1927-1991
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1964-004
4.5 cu. ft. 3 boxes
Records of the Virginia Social Science Association, including correspondence, minutes, programs, committee reports, working files for annual meetings, financial and membership records.
Virginia Social Science Association.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Virginia Social Science Association Records were donated to Special Collections in several accruals, dated 1964, 1965, 1966, 1978, 1987, 1989, and 1992.
Historical Note
The Virginia Social Science Association (VSSA) was founded at the University of Virginia on May 8, 1926, in a meeting arranged by W. E. Garnett of Virginia Polytechnic Institute. Established "to provide a common meeting ground for men and women of the academic, professional and pragmatic realms who are working or interested in the social sciences--in those sciences which deal with man's everyday human relationships with his fellow-man--economics, sociology, history, political science and law," the association had 59 charter members and within three years had grown to nearly 200. The group held its initial annual conference at VPI in 1927, with the location changing with each successive year. Since 1966, the VSSA has published the Virginia Social Science Journal
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the records of the Virginia Social Science Association, including correspondence, committee minutes and reports, annual meeting programs and working files, presentation papers, committee reports, and financial and membership records.
The correspondence contains letters to and from various organizational officials, as well as committee reports, financial statements, membership lists, and other materials. Included is correspondence of the association's various secretary-treasurers from 1936 to 1960. From 1961 to 1967, the correspondence is comprised of the files of George T. Blume, who served in turn as VSSA secretary-treasurer, vice-president, president, and publications committee chair during those years. Also included is the correspondence of VSSA presidents R. Wayne McCubbins (1972-1973), John Wood (1973-1974), Charles Lane (1975-1976), and Arthur B. Gunlicks (1976-1977). The collection also includes the correspondence of James F. Herndon, who served as VSSA president and on the executive, development awards, and ad hoc self-study committees during the years 1980-1990, and as the local arrangements chair for the VSSA's 1989 annual meeting, held at Virginia Tech. Also included is correspondence of Catherine Seaman, VSSA president from 1987 to 1988.
Though the collection includes a small selection of files from committees, much of the material relating to committee work is filed with the correspondence and the annual meeting papers. The files devoted to the annual meetings also include business meeting minutes, programs, registration lists, and correspondence on planning and presentations, as well as presentation texts.
The collection also includes copies of the association's newsletter, VSSA News; financial records, including receipts, account statements, and audit reports; and files on membership and subscriptions, including mailing lists.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by file type, including correspondence, committees, annual meetings, newsletters, financial records and membership lists.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Volumes of the Virginia Social Science Journal and the VSSA's published annual proceedings may be located using the library's catalog.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Virginia Agricultural and Mechanical College and Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Local Subjects:
University Archives
Contents List
- Correspondence
  - 1936-1939 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - 1940 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - 1941, [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-3)
  - 1942 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - 1943-1944 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - 1945 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - 1946, [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-7)
  - 1947 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - 1948, [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-9)
  - 1949, [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-10)
  - 1950 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - 1951 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - 1952 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - 1953 (Box-folder 1-14)
  - 1954 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - 1955 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - 1956 (Box-folder 1-17)
  - 1957 (Box-folder 1-18)
  - 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - 1960-1961 (Box-folder 1-20)
  - 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1-21)
  - 1964, [2 folders] (Box-folder 1-22)
  - 1965 (Box-folder 1-23)
  - 1966-1967 (Box-folder 1-24)
  - 1972-1977 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - 1981-1983 (Box-folder 1-26)
  - 1984-1986 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - 1987 (Box-folder 1-28)
  - 1988 (Box-folder 2-1)
  - 1989-1991, n.d. (Box-folder 2-2)
- Committees
  - Awards, 1972-1983 (Box-folder 2-3)
  - Curriculum, [1930]-1940 (Box-folder 2-4)
  - Executive, 1927-1989, [4 folders] (Box-folder 2-5)
  - Membership, 1939-1940 (Box-folder 2-6)
  - Nominating, 1974 (Box-folder 2-7)
  - Policy, 1949 (Box-folder 2-8)
  - Public opinion, 1930-1934 (Box-folder 2-9)
  - Publications, 1936-1939, n.d. (Box-folder 2-10)
  - Research, 1928-1941, n.d., [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-11)
  - Resolutions, 1963-1975 (Box-folder 2-12)
  - Social science instruction, 1948-1949, n.d. (Box-folder 2-13)
  - Student chapters, 1938-1940 (Box-folder 2-14)
- Annual meeting proceedings and working files
  - Constitution, 1928-1988, n.d. (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Business meeting minutes, 1927-1949 (Box-folder 2-16)
  - Programs, 1927-1985 (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Registration lists, 1934-1953, n.d. (Box-folder 2-18)
  - Yearbook, 1929 (Box-folder 2-19)
  - Annual meeting, [1935] (Box-folder 2-20)
  - Annual meeting, 1939, [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-21)
  - Annual meeting, 1940 (Box-folder 2-22)
  - Annual meeting, 1942 (Box-folder 2-23)
  - Annual meeting, 1944 (Box-folder 2-24)
  - Annual meeting, 1946, [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-25)
  - Annual meeting, 1947 (Box-folder 2-26)
  - Annual meeting, 1949, [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-27)
  - Annual meeting, 1956 (Box-folder 2-28)
  - Annual meeting, 1974 (Box-folder 2-29)
  - Annual meeting, 1975 (Box-folder 2-30)
  - Annual meeting, 1976 (Box-folder 2-31)
  - Annual meeting, 1977 (Box-folder 2-32)
  - Annual meetings, 1978-1983 (Box-folder 2-33)
  - Annual meeting, 1987, [2 folders] (Box-folder 2-34)
  - Annual meeting, 1988 (Box-folder 2-35)
  - Annual meeting, 1989 (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Annual meetings, 1990-1991 (Box-folder 3-2)
- VSSA News
  - Newsletters,1970-1971 (Box-folder 3-3)
  - Newsletters, 1972-1975 (Box-folder 3-4)
  - Newsletters, 1983-1990 (Box-folder 3-5)
- Financial records
  - Ledgers, 1936-1955 (Box-folder 3-6)
  - Invoices and account statements, 1935-1959 (Box-folder 3-7-14)
- Membership and mailing lists
  - Mailing lists, 1935-1947 (Box-folder 3-15)
  - Mailing lists, 1948-1952 (Box-folder 3-16)
  - Mailing lists, 1955-1957, n.d. (Box-folder 3-17)
  - Memberships, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 3-18)
  - Memberships, 1981-1989 (Box-folder 3-19)
  - Membership lists, n.d. (Box-folder 3-20)
  - Institutional memberships/subscriptions, 1968-1973 (Box-folder 3-21)
  - Institutional memberships/subscriptions 1974-1975 (Box-folder 3-22)
  - Past presidents project, 1974 (Box-folder 3-23)
  - Membership cards, 1952-1960 (Box-folder 3-24)
  - Membership cards, 1961-1962, n.d. (Box-folder 3-25)